Guide to the Montana School of Mines Records, 1901-1963
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives
Montana School of Mines records
1901-1963
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives
Montana School of Mines
RS 69
0.75 linear feet
This collection consists of primarily of correspondence of George W. Craven, the president of the State School of Mines (currently Montana Technological University) from 1921-1928, as well as financial records and publications.
In 1893, the Montana State Legislature authorized the creation of the Montana State School of Mines in Butte, Montana, for the purpose of offering engineering education. The school opened for classes in September 1900 and admitted both men and women. Nathan R. Leonard presided as the first president of the School of Mines. Originally, the school offered two degrees in the areas of mining engineering and electrical engineering.
In 1918, the school was renamed the State School of Mines. In 1919, the Montana Legislature enacted a bill creating the State Bureau of Mines and Metallurgy. The president of the school served as head of the Bureau.
In 1921, George W. Craven became president of the school. Born in Last Chance Gulch in April 1871, Craven obtained a B.S. in Electrical Engineering from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and worked at several mining companies before joining the faculty at the School of Mines in 1905. He became the school's first vice-president in 1919, and in 1921, he succeeded C.H. Clapp as president. Craven served as president until 1928.
Over the years, the school adjusted curricula and degree offerings to suit the demands of the time. Graduate degrees were offered beginning in 1929. During World War II, the School of Mines participated in the V-12 Navy College Training Program and provided training for hundreds of Naval officers. The school also underwent a series of name changes. In 1965, it became the Montana College of Mineral Science and Technology, and then in the 1990s, it became Montana Tech of the University of Montana. As of 2021, the school's name is Montana Technological University.
This collection consists primarily of correspondence during President George Craven's administration. Incoming letters are addressed to Craven both as President and State Consulting Engineer. The correspondence concerns the daily running of the school, as well as construction projects. Materials in the collection also include, a cash ledger, a journal for the library and miscellaneous school publications.
The collection is arranged by material type; thereunder chronologically when feasible. Most of the correspondence is organized alphabetically by name of sender.
This collection is open for research.
Most of the materials in this collection were donated.
Photographs were transferred to the photo archives, and one map was transferred to the library.
The Montana Historical Society holds records for the University of Montana System that contain additional information about the Montana School of Mines. Contact the Research Center Archives for details.
Craven, George W. (George Warren), 1871-1936--Correspondence
Montana School of Mines; (Butte, Mont.). Montana School of Mines; Montana College of Mineral Science and Technology; Montana School of Mines; Montana. State School of Mines, Butte; Montana Tech of the University of Montana
Education, Higher; School buildings--Design and construction; Mining schools and education--Montana--Butte
Montana; Colleges and Universities
- Incoming correspondence, A-D, 1922-1923; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Correspondents include B. Adelstein; Advance Machinery and Supply Company; American Academy of Political and Social Science; American Association of Petroleum Engineers; American District Steam Company; American Wood Pipe Company; Biltmore Industries; Butte Specialty Company; Colorado Atomized Fuel Company; Colorado Sporting Goods Company; Combustion Engineering Company; Michael V. Conroy; Durand Steel Locker Company
- Incoming correspondence, E-H, 1922-1923; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Correspondents include E.H. Sheldon and Company, re laboratory equipment; Esterbrook Steel Pen Manufacturing Company; Four Wheel Drive Auto Company; Fuel Economy Engineering Company; Steve Guilio; M.F. Graupner; Helena Concrete Pipe Company; Highway Education Board; R.C. Hugenin
- Incoming correspondence, I-L, 1922-1923; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Correspondents include Illinois Steel Company; F.R. Ingalsbe; Mrs. F.M. Kaupish; Keasbey and Mattison Company; Kimball Brothers Company; W.R. Landwehr; Thomas Large
- Incoming correspondence, M, 1922-1923; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Correspondents include W.N. McCormick; Montana Soldiers' Home; Montana Purchasing Agent; Montana State Board of Examiners; Montana State Board of Health; Montana State Hospital for the Insane; Morse Chain Company; Mosby Electric Company
- Incoming correspondence, N-T, 1922-1923; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Correspondents include C.J. Nepper; Jack Nuckols; Northwestern National Bank Review; Permutit Company; Playground and Recreation Association of America; Rocky Mountain Faculty Conference; Thomas A.X. Shannon; P.A. Slattendale; Twin Bridges Consolidated Schools
- Incoming correspondence, U-W, 1922-1923; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Correspondents include U.S. Civil Service Commission; U.S. Tariff Commission; U.S. Veterans Bureau; University of Montana Chancellor's Office [H.H. Swain]; University of Montana State School of Mines; State University Missoula; University of the Philippines; Walsh Fire Clay Products Company
- Outgoing correspondence, 1922-1923; 5 folders (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
- Correspondence, 1920-1923 and undated; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Library Ledger, 1916-1925; 1 folders (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes text-book orders
- Cash Ledger, 1901; 1 folders (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Publications, 1937-1963; 1 folders (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Includes a commencement program from 1937